so uh the purpose of this particular
class we are trying to go we're trying
to get through a text uh which was
taught by my teacher's teacher so my
teacher's teacher was T who was the D
Lama's
teacher and then uh T's teacher was B
and then he gave this teaching in Tibet
1921 24 day teaching and then P the D
tutor spent most of his life uh turning
it into a really I believe for me it's
the most beautiful book I've ever read
and I and I live with books right uh and
then my teacher
spent over 20 years uh teaching it to us
and then I thought uh it would be a
shame if I didn't pass this on in my
lifetime sometime so we've been
uh it's a it's a outline of the steps to
Enlightenment so it's a very uh
traditional Tibetan and Indian
Buddhist uh teaching whereby you learn
the steps to Enlightenment one by one as
you go through the book and then there's
a custom called Yami where you it's the
fif Lama was very keen on U where you
study one of the steps of the maybe
there are 20 steps okay so you study one
of the 20 steps to Enlightenment and
then you go out in the forest with
everybody and you meditate on it for
like 10 days together and you try to go
deep into it and try to get an
experience of that path not so I'm I'm
just giving you the driver's manual and
then in January we'll start
driving okay so I'm reading you the
driver's manual which is kind of in
itself kind of weird right sit and talk
about meditation it's like talking about
yoga day after day and then you know
then after that you got to go do it
right so uh we'll go driving in January
all right and the idea is that we will
continue that way for 10 it will take 10
years to finish this book if we stick to
my original schedule which we're already
behind uh but anyway let's call it 10
years uh and it will take two study
sessions of 10 days a year like this one
and then two tend treats in you in which
we try to internalize and actually gain
a spiritual experience of of that step
okay so we we thought we would go to the
end of the book cover the last great two
steps which are how to get
into the deepest state of meditation you
need to see Ultimate Reality and then a
discussion of what that Ultimate Reality
is like okay so we thought we would go
to the end of the book uh cover those
two subjects and then go to the
beginning of the book in our next 10day
session in
April and start from the beginning
applying our knowledge of meditation and
applying our knowledge of Ultimate
Reality to each subject so for example
one of the
earliest steps of the steps enlightment
is to is a meditation about your death
you you we're trained in the Monastery
when you go to bed you do a meditation
on your death you actually take yourself
through
the they call it the Domino collapse the
the collapse of your body as you go
through the death process so and what it
will look like what it will feel like we
practice it every night in the month's
day you lay your head on the pillow you
start your death meditation
right that has a profound effect on you
uh in your life you don't waste time you
know you get very sensitive to your
mortality and your
fedility and then then you everything
you do is is what do you call it has
more uh intensity to it your life
everything you do you get very good at
thinking this is your last day and then
whether you're you know making out with
your spiritual partner or whether you're
are building your cabin or whether you
are you know meditating everything takes
on a much much deeper intensity and a
sweetness you know like I'm leaving you
tomorrow you know let's put a good door
on this cabin or you know uh you you get
very intense in a beautiful way in a
soft gentle beautiful way you become
very intense you don't waste your time
even if you go out for a movie it's
intense you know and you you get into
the movie because if it was the last
movie you ever saw you'd wanted to be a
good one you know and you're more choosy
about your movies uh
but to do that death meditation with a
with a deep capacity for meditation if
you could go deep deep deep into your
own death in
meditation and if you could apply the
principles of emptiness to your
mortality you could overcome that
mortality
itself you would not
die so rather than going through the
book in the normal order we've gone to
the back of the book which is how to go
into a state of deep meditation and how
to manipulate reality itself the
$158,000 chair coming on the first day
that ACI open is not an accident right
it was a reality tweaking exercise
right by the way we should we should
thank Harry Goodman right
Goodman uh who passed the way not
thanking for passing away but he he
passed away I didn't know him personally
but he donated that money to us for this
to start these teaching okay and it came
on the day we started if you would like
to if you understand an aness deeply and
if you learn to meditate in a powerful
way you can
affect uh the events of your world and
and if enough people were working on it
uh we could remove hunger and we could
remove
poverty uh by understanding the source
code for for for life
itself the events of History we you can
tweak them and you can send them off on
a in a different direction at will and
checks will show up on the day you start
the the center in Phoenix all right back
from somebody you never met okay and uh
you
can then you can use that to help the
people in the world and that's the point
that's the point of what we're doing can
you learn to
tweak reality and history itself in such
a way that poverty hunger war and death
itself in this world be becom something
that used to happen and not something
that happens anymore people will teach
it in history books people used to die
people used to kill each other there
used to be people die from Hunger people
used to get a thing called cancer and it
will all be past tense you know there
are places like that and and then we
just have to work on it a bit here and
you will be the ones to do it okay so
anyway here we
go uh he was using different arguments
to prove that you yourself are not who
you thought you were whether your name
is Rob or Nat or or Darren or Rebecca it
doesn't you uh it doesn't matter who you
are he was going into arguments that
would demonstrate to
ourselves that we are not who we thought
we were if you
are who you thought you were if you
exist out there as a solid uh thing
which is coming this way and not this
way you know if you are not coming from
your own seeds in your mind but if
rather you were born from your mother's
womb and you walk through this life in
the way we think then you must
die and and there's
no cure for the world the world's pain
then if things exist that way then then
we can't really change anything right if
rather the world and ourselves are
coming from seeds in our mind that we
plant there by taking care of other
people then all things are possible then
you can then you can make changes in the
world right then you can plant different
the fourth chapter of the
yoga right we must become as Farmers or
gardeners right we if if the world is
really deriving from seeds in our own
mind which are planted by how well we
take care of others then everything is
doable everything is changeable your own
mortality is is coming from actually
your mortality is coming from the what
do you call
the you call when you spend expend
expending of the Seas right you are you
are expending seeds by
living and those seeds wear out and then
you die so if you knew a way to what do
you call
it
uh to re replant the
seeds like reinvest but is there some of
the
word yeah regenerate the seeds if you
knew how to plant more seeds for life
itself rather than simply using up your
old seeds it's like you start life with
a credit card and you're always drawing
on it if you knew how to make a
deposit uh to that credit card you
wouldn't die right we just don't know
how to do that we are by living by the
act of living we are using up the seeds
in our mind which make us see ourselves
as a life and unless we plant more seeds
consciously in our mind then we will die
and if you do plant more seeds
consciously in your mind you
won't um so there are there are many uh
Arguments for why you are not who you
thought you were right like I have to
convince you that you are coming from
seeds in your mind which means I have to
convince you that you're not who you
thought youm and then one of those
arguments is
called okay
[Music]
say okay so he mentions n but he doesn't
explain
it and I thought you maybe you'd like to
have a good explanation of it uh it's
very very very difficult uh proof of why
you're not who you thought you were and
uh I'm going to give you uh this is from
a uh an ancient Indian teacher named
gananda uh probably around sixth or
seventh century but but he gave a good
explanation of it
okay so so in the back of the car when
nimo's driving us
around because of the kindness because
of the hard work of the Tibetan women
refugees uh I can ask the computer you
know where's the best explanation of
this weird ancient proof that you're not
yourself and it will go through a
million pages in about 10 seconds and
and and spit spit out to me the best
explanation okay so here it is and and
we have to keep going
on so this comes as I said last night
from a very
ancient uh discussion very beautiful
discussion uh
between a king named
menander who was one of the Greek Kings
who took over Baka uh Afghanistan and
India and he was left there by Alexander
the Great right and then there was a
custom in ancient times very very
beautiful custom
that Kings would seek out the advice of
yogis and and it's very very beautiful
Alexander the Great himself met a a
delegation of yogis in a place called
taxila which the Tibetan called Bodo and
it's very beautiful so outside of tuilla
uh there's a beautiful record of
Alexander the Great Meeting the yogis
and he took one back with him uh he died
on the way Alexander died I think in
bdan but
but the yogi made it back to Greece and
affected Western
thinking and uh so this Greek king named
menander met a met a Buddhist monk an
Indian Buddhist monk and 200 BC right
and then they started to they have a
discussion which was recorded and exists
still in Nepali okay in Sri Lanka and we
we have that text and and we Tau that
text for a while
um and that set the scene for Thomas the
disciple Thomas to come to takilla also
uh he was brought to takilla by another
king named the the Greeks call him G the
forest uh which is uh one of the three
kings who greeted the birth of Jesus
okay so he's one of the three wise men
who came to make offerings at the day of
Jesus he went back to
Taka he he he needed an architect and
you know the story Thomas ended up in
India he died in U Janai
Madras he was martyred in Madras so
anyway this
conversation uh continued in Gilla for a
long time if Christianity affected
Buddhist
thinking it could well be that Jesus's
teachings help triggered the middle way
sorry the Mahayana movement of
compassion in Buddhism and uh so this
teaching comes from a that time period
when there was a lot of interaction okay
so here it is the idea is
that we have to examine the
impossibility of a chariot okay they say
a chariot uh you can call it a car all
right I think a car would be more
comfortable for us
um in
examining uh whether or not you've
always been making a a tragic mistake
about who you are you can examine a uh a
car and how you perceive a car and if
you uh once you figure it out with a car
you can apply it to Michael okay
so means we look at the relationship
between a car and it's Parts in seven
different ways I'll I'll just give you
an overview all right
when you look at a
car when you go out in the parking lot
and your eyes turn left and you see
something called a car right
uh to to what you call to identify it as
an automobile you have to be able to see
a
few what do you call it crucial parts or
what do you call it definitive parts of
a of an automobile right there has to be
a decent number of classical automobile
pieces there for you to call it a car
okay like it should have four wheels
traditionally I mean normally uh if you
glance at it and it doesn't have four
wheels we can I'm calling it a working
car okay a working car I'm not saying a
car in a junkard uh a working car you
know a car in normal condition uh you
glance at the object and you glance away
if your eye catch is four round black
things and a hood and a top and
especially if you look through the
window and you see a driving wheel
driving wheel Ste steering wheel
sorry uh then then you're based on those
parts you know I'm just talking it's a
very very deep subject this is what GMA
uh writes about how did you know it was
a car you glan to the left coming out of
the church you saw an object in the
parking lot I mean the clue that it's in
a parking lot is already a clue right I
mean it could be uh I don't know
anything could be an elephant but you
you look over and you see four black
round shapes your eye understand one
thing your eye is not capable of seeing
objects things the eye only records
colors and shapes the rods and cones of
the eye are not capable in and of
themselves of deciding what an object is
they simply transmit colors and shades
to the mind to the brain okay they can't
the decision on what the lumpy thing is
in the parking lot is not made in the
back of the eyeball because it's not
equipped to do that it
only uh the rods and cones are changed
by the image of the car hitting the
front of the eye and then the rods and
cones the chemical
changes uh information is sent to the
mind this is all the information that
can be sent to the mind when you glance
left at the thing in the parking lot
black or
round okay about 2 3T High you know like
there's somebody on the phone from the
back of your eyeball to your brain and
they they can't the only information
they can transmit is is numbers or
colors or how many shapes round blacks
four round blacks we got four round
blacks down here uh there's a thinner
round thing behind the transparent
thing and uh there's the front is
stretched out in a certain way and
there's a certain cockpit look to it you
know he doesn't say cockpit okay uh and
then there
are white
flashes uh these are bumpers right but
he doesn't know there's white flashes in
the the front and white light white long
flashes in the front and silver long
flashes in the front and the back okay
so that that information is all that the
eye can see that goes to the mind then
the
mind
uh has to synthesize a whole from the
heart right the mind has
to PE piece together a picture of what
was seen uh based on the information we
see okay so we we are in a parking lot
we're in what we know to be a parking
lot uh there's four blocks they're round
there's a another round inside and uh
there's two silver long flashes front
and back um let's see I think it must be
a car right and then the
mind uh you see a car you see a whole
car right
so is it
possible to see the car
without seeing the pieces of the
car is it possible no you can't see a
whole
car if if you glanced left and saw a
whole car you wouldn't see the
tires and you wouldn't see the
bumpers and you wouldn't see theing okay
if you glanc to the left and
saw
car uh you would by definition You' have
to be seeing the whole thing am I right
I mean otherwise you'd say I'm seeing
wheel you see if if you focus on the
black round thing wheel and you turn
away all you can say is I saw a wheel
all right so somehow when you glance
left you see a whole thing right you
have to see a whole thing or you don't
see your car otherwise you're seeing a
bumper or a a wheel or a steering wheel
that's
uh you don't see a whole car when you
are looking at the wheels you don't see
a whole car when you are looking at the
steering wheel you don't see a whole car
can but can you see the whole car if you
don't see those things no cuz you can't
recognize it as a car you must see a
whole thing and then you must focus in
on different pieces that are indic indic
indicative indic IND
indicative of a car right cannot see a
whole car unless you see the part of the
car all right you can't see a whole
wheel unless you
see the left and right side of the wheel
right you can't see the left side of the
wheel unless you see the top of the left
side of the wheel and the bottom of the
right side ofel it's not possible right
it's not possible to confirm that it's a
car you must be able to detect visually
indicators of a car things which
indicate a car all
right cannot see the whole car unless
you see the parts of the car when you
see the parts of the car do you see the
car it's not possible it's not possible
if you're looking at the tire you're not
seeing the car am I right if you're
staring at the tire you're not seeing
the
car right am I right yeah if you're
staring at the tire you can't see the
car it's not possible
uh you can't see the whole car without
staring at the car if you stare at the
tire you can't see the whole
car I'll say it again you can't see a
whole
car unless you see
Tire if you see a tire you can't be
seeing the whole
time and this is what I'm trying to say
it sounds like I'm just making some joke
or something I'll say it one more time
you can't tell it's a car unless you
look at the wheels tires if you do look
at the tires you're not looking at the
car anymore all
right can't see the car unless you see
the tires and if you are seeing the
tires you can't see the
car but you do it
somehow understand one thing just get
one thing and that's enough for today
right we're close to uh five we got 10
more minutes or something
just understand try to grasp one
thing when you think you're seeing a car
it's not possible what you think you
move all right you cannot be seeing a
car it's not
possible that little uh what do you call
it conundrum that I just stated which
was you can't see the whole car unless
you you can't identify unless you look
at the tis if you do look at the tis you
can't see the whole car by definition
you see the whole
car can't see the car unless you see the
tires and if you do see the tires you
can't see the car what you think you're
looking at is not
possible what you think is going on is
not possible this is just one of a
thousand Arguments for emptiness all
right it's just one you could do the pen
thing you could do the aspon thing this
is num Beau this is very very ancient uh
from just from just of the time of uh
Alexander the Great and his teacher
named Aristotle who sent a guy along
with Alexander to keep eye and eye on
him and he Alexander killed him that's
another St um that's a way to get rid of
irritating
teaching
so
uh but try to try to struggle okay you
you go home today at least for one or
two days try to struggle with this okay
you cannot be seeing what you think
you're seeing
not possible you cannot be seeing a car
or or people or a church and most
importantly you cannot be
seeing yourself in the mirror it's not
possible you can't be who you thought
you were it's not it's not possible
which is lucky because if you were who
you thought you were death would be
inevitable and you could not change the
your nature if if you were you think you
are from inside
yourself then if the car was a car from
the car side everything can't be changed
do you know the only way you can change
a thing that's out there is to take a
sledgehammer and bang on it and you know
like that but that's not how a car
exists here's the real poop
okay
uh you come out of
the and this is extremely profound I I
this talk at Princeton University a
couple weeks ago and these two
physicists freaked
out so anyway
um I was going to show that yeah Quant
mechanics thing anyway next time uh it's
kind of
distracting
uh but this is very profound and it can
change your life you can get $158,000
checks at the last minute when you need
them uh you can change bones in your
body you can see emptiness directly you
can save the world you can become the
person who contributes to this world
moving beyond war and hunger okay you
can do those things if you understand
what I'm about to say right wait I'm
going to
try when you come out of the church and
you glance at a car what's really
happening is that you see your eye does
see certain indicators okay four black
rounds two long Silvers front and back
and a thinner round uh thing behind some
clear squares called Windows
right you do see those indicators your
eye passes over the things and the you
do see the those indicators of an object
that is
true but but everything from then on is
not true what happens
then the information is sent to your
mind and your mind synthesizes a c your
mind makes a picture of a car an
impossibly perfect picture of a car
because you can see four
wheels you feel like you see four wheels
can you you can really you can see
pieces of them maybe if you get down low
enough anyway your mind Fashions an
image of a car
right and and you're not looking at a
car from then from that moment from that
point in the process on you are watching
an image in your own head you are
looking at an image in your own mind
that's not meant to freak you out okay
can you drive that image to the store
yes yes that's extremely important to
understand that when I say that perfect
car that you think you see is an image
in your own mind don't make the mistake
of thinking it's not real that's
what makes
it CU there was never or any other kind
of car because the other kind of car was
impossible we already talked about that
the car you thought was there was not
possible there has never been any car
like that in the parking lot and there
couldn't be okay the way you think cars
are it's not possible the cars you've
ever seen in your life were all pictures
in your mind and your mind was
projecting it out was the car outside of
you yes because your mind was projecting
it outside of you all right is the car
outside of your mind yes is it an image
of your mind yes can you drive to the
store yes yes
okay
why because it is coming from your mind
all right you got to feel comfortable
with
that because if it wasn't coming from
your mind it wouldn't be a car because
there's no such thing it's not possible
we already talked about that didn't we
already talk about that say yes you can
get home
then you know a lot of teachers stop
there they say okay that's all the class
that's emptiness see you next week you
know but you got
to you got to talk about something you
got to talk about how do you use that in
your life you know okay so I thought the
car was out there now you've proved that
the car is coming from my
mind what's that do for me you know why
should I you know invest years of my
life studying the these things if I
can't use it for anything what's the
point of saying that the car's coming
from your life now why do you why even
if it's true what's the point I mean why
why what do I care you know I don't care
if $100 is coming from the out there or
in here I just want $100 you know
um if it's coming from inside your mind
you can control the
process if it's coming from inside your
mind you can can create the things you
want a war a world without War a world
without hunger you see if the world is
coming from inside your mind if it's
being sent out by your mind then you can
solve the problems of the world this is
why we're learning this okay it's not
just some philosophy class at Princeton
you know I I knew those guys they sit
around you can't even talk to them
they're
like you say is the sky blue and they
say well we'll have to think about that
you know and you couldn't talk to them I
had tried to hire one one time I had a
little company it didn't work um he
couldn't drive a truck he kept running
in into
trees and then he discussed the
tree it's not philosophy it's a life or
death for six billion people it's life
[Music]
or it's life or death for 6 billion
people if you get it you can change
things if you don't you can't okay if
the poverty and hunger of the world is
coming from economic events or or lack
of material resources then then it's
hopeless uh if the hunger and poverty
the world is coming from us then we can
tweak things and and remove it right
so why does your mind draw the
conclusion that these parts are a car
this is the Crux of the talk and we'll
stop okay get this and we'll
stop why does your mind conclude why
does your mind synthesize from those
black rounds and those silver lungs why
does it synthesize a
c that you can use to go to a teaching
that could change the
world
huh yeah you have been kind to
someone with all
you planted the seed for your mind to
see a car you planted the seed for your
mind to throw forth an image of a car to
fit the
indicators uh of four black rounds two
long
Silvers your mind chose that image which
is a reasonable image okay it's a
reasonable image your mind shows that
image from among many other IM
just because you had a seed for seeing a
car in your mind because you had a seed
for seeing a car that you could use in
your mind how was that seed planted in
your mind and then we can stop by prise
how was that seed planted in your
mind you gave people
right especially the poor especially the
elderly especially the heless people of
the world right the people who get on
the
buses right you gave them a right you
stopped you said hey we need to ride and
we took them somewhere that kindness
right kindness runs the images of the
entire world right kindness is the
[Music]
real substance of the world right is not
physical it's it's you have done
something good to someone else and that
could have seen in your life
then your mind chooses car your mind
chooses a picture of a
car to put on those pieces because you
been clined to someone with the car
right you use the car to serve somebody
and then your mind throws forth an image
of the car see it's very very beautiful
so your kindness is creating all the
objects around you so you have to be
kind you don't have a choice you you
have to be kind and then if everyone me
to be kind
everybody have a
car I was in Germany recently you know
then this guy raes he says J that's the
problem I said what he says can you
imagine the
pollution then I said no no you don't
know where the SE from pollution is
coming
from you just make an electric car with
your
M and uh he was okay that all right so
we made a really good
Karm we made a really really well that's
not that's one of the seven okay but
anyway Ming you have to remember where
we stopped from next Air okay
[Laughter]
[Applause]
[Music]
well that was a hard
point so no I could just roll over that
point and people do right but you should
know what it is right uh okay
anyway uh we did a really good
karma uh we we talked about things that
could change the whole world and
uh as I mentioned before the world is
changing you are changing in the world
weird things are
happening British Air called $12 billion
company called Could you teach 43,000
employees about this stuff you know like
if British Airways is willing to try it
you should be willing to try it okay and
uh you you will be the people who bring
these ideas to the world okay you will
be the people whether you're going to
the three Retreat and they bid you well
or whether you're staying uh outside and
and serving people in another way if you
really learn these things well then you
can change this world and what I'm
saying is the British Airways thing
shows that it shows that it's possible
we can
affect thousands of people they they
carry 37 million, a year if we affect
those 43,000 workers then then
then strange things can happen when you
start going into the core of your mind
with the meditation instructions that we
studied all week and at the core of your
mind you can make very weird changes to
reality and the world will change okay
because it's coming from the core of
your mind
so uh make a decision that you will
learn this this teaching right it will
take 10 years the good things take time
and then uh you will pass it on to other
people in your in your own time you know
you will carry to the next okay M you
have to try okay you have to make a
commitment to learn it and then pass it
on to others then we can change the
world then we can help the world okay Ma
I'm asking you one more time it wasn't
very
good all right